in my most un-TED-like garb. And there was an act, an act known as the Oracle Act. And in the Oracle Act, members of the audience, as I know you have done, would write down secret questions, the sort of questions you might ask a psychic, seal that question into an envelope, and on the outside of the envelope they would write their initials and then roughly where they sat in the audience. And then the Oracle, the mind reader, would take an envelope one at a time,
Con mi mejor traje anti-TED. Y hubo un acto conocido como el acto del Oráculo. En este acto, los miembros del público, como Uds. lo han hecho hoy, escribían preguntas secretas, el tipo de preguntas que harían a un vidente. Después guardaban la pregunta en un sobre, escribían por fuera sus iniciales y su lugar aproximado de asiento. Después, el Oráculo, el que leía mentes, tomaba los sobres uno a uno,
he wouldn't open it, but he would attempt to divine what question was sealed inside. And if he got that right, he would try and answer the question for the person too. And the act spread like wildfire. It's a testament, I think, to the seductive appeal of some powerful figure offering you easy, simple answers to life's complex and subtle questions and anxieties.
no los abría, pero intentaba adivinar qué pregunta estaba guardada dentro. Y si acertaba, intentaba responder a la pregunta por la persona que la redactó. Este espectáculo se extendió como la pólvora. Creo que es una prueba sobre el aspecto seductor de una figura poderosa ofreciéndote respuestas simples y sencillas a las complicadas y sutiles preguntas y ansiedades de la vida.
So thank you all of you that wrote questions. I haven't seen these. I know somebody's guarding them. Thank you so much. I will take those now. Thank you all of you that did this. I should say, probably, a couple of things before I start. In absolute honesty, first of all I can't see through these envelopes. They are sealed. They are thick black envelopes. You'll know if you wrote one. I can't see through them. Secondly, importantly, I don't know any of you and nobody is playing along. That's not what this is. Thirdly ... I don't believe for a second that I have any special psychological gifts, let alone any psychic ones. So let's begin. Nope. (Laughter) OK, this -- Oh, nice. OK, this one's interesting. There's a couple here. I will start with maybe this one. This one's interesting, because the writing undulates. There's a sort of an up and down thing, which normally -- not always -- normally means that the person doesn't know the answer to the question themselves, so it's normally a question about the future, right? That sort of suggests uncertainty. So I would say it's a lady, age-wise it's a little difficult to tell from this minimal handwriting, but I would expect maybe 30s, maybe 40s, but let's find out. It says -- and a question about the future -- it says, "JN, center." So it's going to be somebody in this big central section here. If you think this is you, if you wrote one, could you make a fuss? It's a bit difficult for me to see in the center. Hi, give us a wave. So J ... Jane? Jessica? Jessica: Yes. Derren Brown: Which one? Jessica: Jessica. DB: Thank you. Just a guess. Little murmur of approval, thank you? (Laughter) I'll take it. Alright, so Jessica, I won't ask your age, but is it a question essentially about the future? Jessica: Mhm? DB: Yes? Jessica: Yes. DB: Yes. OK. Alright. So what did we ask? What did Jessica ask about the future? So am I OK with late-30s, early-40s?
Gracias a los que hoy escribieron preguntas. Yo no las he visto. Sé que alguien las guarda. Muchísimas gracias. Ahora las tomaré. Gracias a todos los que ayudaron. Probablemente debería decir un par de cosas antes de empezar. Si soy totalmente honesto... Primero, no puedo ver a través de los sobres. Están sellados. Son gruesos y negros. Lo sabrán si han escrito uno de ellos. Es imposible. Lo segundo y más importante, no conozco a nadie aquí y nadie me está siguiendo la corriente. No se trata de eso. Tercero... no creo para nada que yo tenga ningún don psicológico y mucho menos psíquico. Así que, comencemos. Nop. (Risas) Bueno, este... Oh, bien. Bueno, este es interesante. Aquí hay un par. Quizás empiece con este. Este es interesante porque la escritura es ondulada. Digamos que sube y baja, que normalmente significa, no siempre que ni siquiera la persona sabe la respuesta a la pregunta. Así que suele ser una pregunta sobre el futuro, ¿no? Eso suele suponer incertidumbre. Así que diría que es una mujer. Respecto a la edad, es difícil saberlo por esta mínima escritura... Yo diría que quizás 30 o 40, pero vamos a averiguarlo. Dice... y una pregunta sobre el futuro, dice: "JN, centro". Así que es alguien de esta sección central de aquí. Si piensan que es alguno de ustedes ¿podrían hacer ruido? Me resulta un poco difícil ver el centro. Hola, salúdanos. J... ¿Jane? ¿Jessica? Jessica: Sí. Darren Brown: ¿cuál de ellos? J: Jessica. DB: Gracias, lo suponía. Unos murmullos de aprobación, por favor. (Risas) Me vale. Bien, no te preguntaré tu edad, pero ¿es una pregunta cuya esencia trata sobre el futuro? J: (Asiente) DB: ¿Sí? Jessica: Sí. DB: Sí. Bien. Bien. ¿Qué hemos preguntado? ¿Qué pregunta Jessica sobre el futuro? ¿Voy bien con lo de los 30, tirando a 40?
Jessica: I'll take it. I'm taking it. (Laughter) DB: OK, so it's important, because we ask different questions depending how old we are. Just say, "I'll take it" again. Jessica: I'll take it. DB: Virginia? You're from Virginia? Jessica: Yes, I am. DB: Yeah. So -- (Laughter) I think this is a lady, I think this is a lady who wants to leave Virginia. I think you're looking at plans, it's whether or not things are going to come together to get out. Just show me your hands. Other sides so I can see fingernails? OK, I think you have a farm and it's whether or not you're going to sell your farm and get out of Virginia? Is this right? Jessica: Absolutely, that's the question. DB: Alright. Great. Thank you. It's a great question! What was the actual question? What did you put? Jessica: "Will I sell the farm in Virginia?" DB: Will you sell the farm? Alright, so look, it's a great question if you are pretending to be psychic, because it's about the future, which means I can give you a yes or no on this. It means nothing. You have no way of verifying it. And a dangerous thing to do -- and if I say yes or no, it'll just stick in the back of your mind, and it can't not start to affect decisions you make. So a dangerous thing to do. However -- (Laughter) Yes, I think you will sell the farm, because I think you're the sort of person that in the nicest way will get what you want. I think when there are things you want, you tend to focus on them at the expense of other things that you know you probably should be focusing on more, would you agree? Educated, you spent a few years in -- Say yes again, the word "yes" quickly? Jessica: Yes. DB: No? Jessica: No. DB: California? Berkeley? A bit of a guess, but ... Jessica: I went to Berkeley, yes. Stop doing this! DB: So it's a yes. Oh, and you've been to India recently as well. There's just a tiny, tiny little thing going on there. Yes? No? Jessica: Yes, I just got back from India. DB: It's a yes from me, I just don't want to say it like it's written in the stars because it isn't, and you need to take responsibility for it. DB: Have a seat. Thank you. Let's do another one. (Applause) AH, also in the center? AH. This will be a man, a little older, maybe late 40s, I would say from this. AH, center, stand up for me if you think this is you. AH. Hi, let's get a microphone to this guy. Quick as we can, on camera would be amazing. Oh, look at that! Freeze. Don't move. Don't move. Keep absolutely still. Are you standing? Where are you?
Jessica: Lo acepto. Me vale. (Risas) DB: Bien, es importante, porque hacemos preguntas distintas dependiendo de la edad. Di "lo acepto" otra vez. Jessica: Lo acepto. DB: ¿Virginia? ¿Es usted de Virginia? Jessica: Sí. DB: Sí. Bien... (Risas) Creo que tenemos a una mujer. Creo que tenemos a una mujer que quiere irse de Virginia. Creo que está haciendo planes, y quieres saber si las cosas van a salir bien o no. Enséñame tus manos. ¿El otro lado para ver las uñas? Vale, creo que tienes una granja y quieres saber si venderás tu granja y te marcharás de Virginia, ¿verdad? ¿Es correcto? Jessica: Totalmente, esa es la pregunta. DB: Bien. Genial. Gracias. ¡Es una gran pregunta! ¿Cuál era la pregunta real? ¿Qué escribió? Jessica: "¿Venderé la granja en Virginia?" DB: ¿Venderás la granja? Bien, mira, es una buena pregunta si simulan ser psíquicos, porque trata sobre el futuro, lo que significa que puedo darles un sí o un no. No significa nada. No hay manera de verificarlo. Y algo peligroso de hacer... si digo sí o no se te quedará dando vueltas en la cabeza, y puede empezar a afectar las decisiones que tomes. Es una accción peligrosa. Pero... (Risas) Sí, creo que venderás la granja porque creo que eres el tipo de persona que consigue lo que quiere de la mejor manera. Creo que cuando se quieren cosas tiendes a centrarte en ellas en detrimento de otras cosas en las que sabes que deberías centrarte más. ¿Estás de acuerdo? Culta, pasaste un par de años en... Dí "sí" otra vez, rápido. Jessica: Sí. DB: ¿No? Jessica: No. DB: ¿California? ¿Berkeley? Solo supongo, pero... Jessica: Fui a Berkeley, sí. ¡Deja de hacer esto! DB: Así que es un sí. ¡Y hace poco has estado en India también! Hay algo por ahí, ¿verdad? ¿o no? Jessica: Sí, acabo de volver de la India. DB: Digo que sí, pero no quiero decirlo como si estuviera destinado a ocurrir, que no lo está, y tienes que asumir la responsabilidad. ¿Contesté a tu pregunta? J: Sí. DB: Siéntate. Hagamos otro. (Aplausos) AH, ¿también en el centro? AH. Este será un hombre, un poco mayor. Por la carta quizás de 40 y muchos. AH, levántate por mí si piensas que eres tú. AH. Hola, demos un micrófono a este chico. Tan rápido como podamos, una cámara sería increíble. ¡Oh, mira eso! Párate. No te muevas. No te muevas. Quédate completamente quieto. ¿Estás de pie? ¿Dónde estás?
Man: I am standing. I'm not that short. DB: OK. Alright, now you changed that. There was just something you did as you got up. Yes or no, have you put something on here --
Hombre: Estoy de pie. No soy tan bajo. DB: Bien. Bien, lo has cambiado. Has hecho algo al levantarte. ¿Sí o no? ¿Has puesto algo aquí...?
you're not doing it now, but you did it as you stood up -- to do with your left or your left leg or your left foot, yes or no? Man: Yes. DB: Alright. He was giving us a nice clear signal as he stood up. Put your weight on your left-hand side and say "yes." Man: Yes. DB: Take your hand out of that pocket, put your weight on the other side, change hands with the mic and say "yes" again. Man: Yes. DB: You have a dislocation in the big toe on your left-hand side? Man: Yes. DB: Thank you so much. Great. Good one! Take a seat. Take a seat. Can I get the microphone? I'm going to change microphone for this. Can I grab a mic up? Thank you. Thank you so much. That would be great there. I'm going to change mic because, hopefully you can now still hear me? So I'm going to blindfold myself. And I'm doing this now so I don't have the clues as you stand up. I can't see where you put your hands. I can't see how you respond to what I'm saying. I can't see what the people next to you are doing either. If they know the answers to the question, that's always very helpful. I won't have those advantages, but strangely, this frees me up, and I want this to free you up as well, so if you didn't write a question but you wish that you had done, you can still take part. The point of writing the question is only that it just kind of gets a nice, clear, succinct wording in your head. So if you can just find a question in your head, make it clear and succinct, just send it to me, and I'll try and do this now without anything written down. So just start to form questions but send me your name as well. "My name is," whatever that last guy was, and "what's strange about my feet," or whatever the question was. So name and question. There is somebody already, I'm guessing you're quite near the front, because your name is quite clear.
Ahora mismo no lo estás haciendo, pero al levantarte, sí. Tiene que ver con tu pierna o tu pie izquierdo. ¿Sí o no? Hombre: Sí. DB: Vale. Nos hizo una señal clara al levantarse. Pon todo el peso en tu lado izquierdo y dime "sí". Hombre: Sí. DB: Sácate la mano del bolsillo y pon el peso en el otro lado, cambia las manos del micrófono y dí "sí". Hombre: Sí. DB: ¿Tienes dislocado el dedo gordo del pie del lado izquierdo? Hombre: Sí. DB: Muchas gracias. Genial. ¡Muy buena! Siéntate. ¿Me pasas el micrófono? Voy a cambiar de micrófono esta vez. ¿Uno para aquí arriba? Gracias. Muchas gracias. Aquí está perfecto. Voy a cambiar de micrófono porque... Todavía pueden oírme, ¿verdad? Voy a vendarme los ojos. Lo haré ahora mismo para no tener pruebas cuando se levanten. No puedo ver donde ponen las manos, cómo responden a lo que les digo, y tampoco puedo ver lo que la persona de al lado hace. Cuando saben las respuestas a la pregunta, siempre resulta muy fácil. No tendré esas ventajas, pero por extraño que suene, esto me libera. Y quiero que los libere a Uds. también, Si no escribieron una pregunta, pero desearían haberlo hecho, todavía pueden participar. El objetivo de escribir una pregunta es que te crea una especie de fórmula corta en la cabeza. Así que si puedes encontrar preguntas en tu cabeza, hacerla clara y concisa, envíamela. Yo intentaré hacerlo sin que haya nada escrito. Así que comiencen a mandarme preguntas con sus nombres. "Me llamo...", seguido del nombre que sea. y "¿qué le ocurre a mi pie?" o lo que sea. O sea, nombre y pregunta. Ya hay alguien. Supongo que estás por la primera fila porque tu nombre está muy claro.
Feels like you're in the center at the front. OK, let me just ... Allan? Feels like there's an Allan. And you're going to be quite near the front, vaguely central, I think. Feels like it's coming from right there. There's like a man, maybe early 60s, something like that. Allan: Yes. DB: You've got a mic? Great, thank you. Allan, just say "stop" when I get to you so that I know where you are, where to face. Allan: Stop. DB: You a Capricorn? Allan: Yes. DB: So Allan has something in his head.
Siento que estás en el centro, por delante. Bien, déjame que... ¿Allan? Siento que hay un Allan. Y debes de estar muy cerca del principio, hacia el centro, creo. Parece que viene por aquí enfrente... Hay un hombre, de unos 60 años, algo así. Allan: Sí DB: ¿Tienes un micrófono? Genial, gracias. Di "para" cuando llegue a ti para saber donde estás, y hacia donde mirar. Allan: Para. DB: ¿Eres Capricornio? Allan: Sí. DB: Allan tiene algo en su cabeza.
Now, did you hear it, hear the reserve in his voice? It's going to be something really tricky. I think with you ... Just say "yes" again for me? Allan: Yes. DB: It's going to be either -- no it's not. It's access, it's a password or access to something. Have you got something, just yes or no, with a password in your head? Allan: Yes. DB: A computer password, that sort of thing?
¿Lo oyen? ¿Oyen la reticencia en su voz? Esto será algo bastante difícil. Yo creo... A ver, dime "sí" otra vez. Allan: Sí. DB: Esto tiene que ser... bueno, no. Es un acceso, una contraseña, para acceder a algo. Dime sí o no. ¿Hay en tu cabeza algo relacionado con una contraseña? Allan: Sí. DB: Una contraseña de computadora, ¿algo así? DB: Excelente. (Risas) En ese caso, voy a terminar ya... Déjame... Si no me equivoco,
they're all going to know what it is, and millions of people potentially. You will change it, won't you? Allan: Of course. (Laughter) DB: Just say "of course" again? Allan: Of course. DB: Alright. If it's a word -- I imagine it's a word, right -- just see the password written in front of you, big clear block capital letters, and as you look at it, think for me of a letter somewhere in the middle, don't say it out loud, just get a letter in your head that's in the middle. Have you got one? Allan: Yeah. DB: OK, stick with that for me. Ah, you changed it, OK. You changed your mind there. I think you settled on a -- I think that's a "B", yes? Allan: No. I didn't. DB: Then it's an "I"? Allan: Correct. DB: But you had a B. Allan: Yes. DB: Yeah, he changed his mind. He changed his mind. (Laughter) So see it written there. Just keep saying it to yourself in your head. Oh, you play drums, don't you. Allan: I do. DB: Just get that out of your head, get that out of your head, just focus on this one thing for me. (Laughter) My job is to sell you a story, right? I try and do this to all of you, to get you to pay attention to one thing that I want you to find important, ignore other things that I want you to ignore, and then join up those narrative dots to tell yourself a certain story about what I'm doing, and this only works because we are story-forming creatures, which means we do this every day. We go out into this complex and subtle world full of a complex and subtle people like you and me, Allan, and we reduce them to these neat characters that fit whatever story we're telling ourselves, and we say, "She's insecure," "He's arrogant," "They can't be trusted." And these are just stories like the story that I can somehow read your mind. You're thinking of selling your company as well, aren't you, at the moment. Allan: Correct. DB: Which is something to do with skin? Allan: Yes. DB: Skin care or something like this. Allan: Uh, yes. DB: And I think the reason why I love doing this is that it reminds me at least to try and be more alive and alert to the complexity and the subtlety of what's real, that there's always other stuff going on that we don't know about, and it means we can get less stuck, we can be kinder to people because we can recognize there's always fear behind their stress, so we don't need to meet it as defensively, and we can start to see the stories for what they are and recognize that life isn't all about us. Oh! Your password, where are you? Where are you? Where is he? Allan: Right here. DB: Stand up for me. Your password is "ariboy." A-r-i-b-o-y? Is that right? Allan: That's correct. DB: Then thank you so much. Thank you very much indeed. Thank you. (Applause)
todo el mundo van a saberla ahora, y millones de personas potencialmene. ¿La cambiarás, verdad? Allan: Por supuesto. (Risas) DB: Di "por supuesto" otra vez? Allan: Por supuesto. DB: Bien. Si es una palabra... Me imagino que es una palabra... Visualiza la palabra escrita frente a ti, en mayúsculas bien grandes, en negrita, y mientras la miras, piensa en una letra en cualquier parte de esa palabra. No la digas en voz alta. Piensa simplemente en una letra por el medio. ¿Ya la tienes? Allan: Sí. DB: Bien, recuérdala. Eh, la has cambiado, bueno. Has cambiado de idea. Creo que al final... has elegido la "B", ¿verdad? Allan: No. No es esa. DB: Bien, ¿es una "I"?. Allan: Sí. DB: Pero antes era una "B". Allan: Sí. DB: Sí, cambiaste de idea. Cambió de idea. (Risas) Bien, imagínatela escrita. Sigue repitiéndola en tu cabeza. ¿Tocas la batería, verdad? Allan: Sí. DB: Olvídate de eso ahora, olvídalo. Ahora concéntrate solo en la palabra. (Risas) Mi trabajo es vender una historia, e intento hacer esto para conseguir dirigir su atención hacia una cosa que quiero que Uds. creen importante. Ignorar otras cosas que quiero que ignoren y después juntar esos nudos narrativos para inventarles una historia sobre lo que hago ahora. Esto funciona porque somos criaturas de crear historias. Lo hacemos todos los días. Salimos a este mundo complejo y sutil lleno de personas complejas y sutiles, como tú y yo, Allan, y las reducimos a estos personajes ordenados que cuadran en cualquier historia que contemos. Y decimos "ella es insegura", "él es arrogante", y otras cosas, y son simplemente historias como la de que les puedo leer la mente. ¿Verdad que en este momento, estás pensando en vender tu empresa? Allan: Correcto. DB: ¿Tiene algo que ver con la piel? Allan: Sí. DB: El cuidado de la piel o algo así. DB: Creo que la razón por la que amo hacer esto es que me recuerda que tengo que estar más vivo y alerta a la complejidad y la sutileza de lo que es real, y que siempre hay otras cosas ocurriendo, que no conocemos. Así, podemos estancarnos menos, ser más amables con los demás porque así siempre podemos reconocer el miedo detrás de su estrés, y no necesitamos tomar todo a la defensiva, y podemos empezar a ver las historias por lo que son y reconocer que todo en la vida no gira entorno a nosotros. ¡Ay! Tu contraseña... ¿Dónde estás? ¿Dónde está? Allan: Aquí. DB: Levántate. Tu contraseña es "ariboy". A-r-i-b-o-y? ¿Correcto? Allan: Sí, correcto. DB: Muchas gracias. Muchas gracias, de verdad. Gracias.